# KAUSHIK DUTTA

(314) 688-1187 \$\Delta \textbf{Email:kaushik.dutta@wustl.edu}\$

LinkedIn:linkedin.com/kaushikdutta & GitHub:github.com/kaushikdutta & Google Scholar:Kaushik Dutta

### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Ph.D candidate in Imaging Science with 4+ years of research experience in deep-learning, applied machine learning, optimization, computer vision, image processing and quantitative data science. Key skills include a strong understanding of machine learning fundamentals, hands-on experience in building and deploying deep-learning frameworks to solve clinical imaging problems along-with strong presentation and communications skills.

### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. in Imaging Science

Washington University in St. Louis; Current GPA: 3.94/4.00

M.S. in Electrical Engineering

Washington University in St. Louis; Degree GPA: 3.94/4.00

St. Louis, USA

B.Tech. in Electronics and Communications Engineering

Heritage Institute of Technology; Degree GPA: 8.86/10.00

Expected August 2024

St. Louis, USA

2019 - 2021

St. Louis, USA

Expected August 2024

St. Louis, USA

St. Louis, USA

B.Tech. in Electronics and Communications Engineering

Kolkata, India

### **SKILLS**

**Programming** Python, MATLAB, R, Java, C/C++, SQL

Libraries/Platforms Tensorflow, Pytorch, Scikit-Learn, SimpleITK, OpenCV, QuPath, ImageJ, AWS, Git Domain Knowledge Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Image Processing, Computer Vision, Algorithm

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Science Intern, Bristol Myers Squibb, New Jersey USA

May 2023 - August 2023

- Developed deep learning based automated frameworks for classification and segmentation of multi-modal medical images to support downstream image analysis pipelines.
- Developed an open-source radiomics pipeline using PyRadiomics to automatically extract features from segmented tumors and predict the overall survival of patients using machine learning
- Utilized machine learning based approach to analyze clinical Real World Data (RWD) and clinical trial data to predict Overall Survival and Response and understand the correlation between primary and secondary endpoints.

Assistant Systems Engineer, Tata Consultancy Services

November 2018 - July 2019

• Designed front-end (UI/UX) using AngularJS and back-end solutions using Java for web-based applications for an insurance company in collaboration with the consultants and client-team.

### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Washington University in St. Louis Doctoral Research Projects:

St. Louis, USA August 2019 - Present

Key Words: Deep Learning, Medical Imaging, Quantitative Imaging

- Developed a deep-learning based pipeline utilizing a novel architecture DR2U-Net specially optimized for tumor segmentation in preclinical multicontrast MR Imaging along-with quantitative validation of radiomics features to tumor probability boundaries. [Paper] [Code]
- Developing deep-learning framework for generation of standard-count PET (SC-PET) images from different realizations of low-count PET (LC-PET) images using supervised and unsupervised learning principle, followed evaluating the quantitative and detection performance of the methods to current clinical standards. [Code]
- Developing deep-learning based correlational network to analyze the correlation and interpretability between radiological and histological biomarkers in assesing therapeutic predictions.

### Coursework Projects:

August 2019 - Present

Key Words: Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Optimization, Imaging

- Automatic Active Neuronal Activity Detection in Calcium Fluorescence Imaging using Bayesian Deep Learning Framework. (Course:Practicum in Imaging Science)
- Predicting Football Match Results using Hierarchical Bayesian Modelling. [Code] (Course: Bayesian ML)
- Densely Connected Recurrent Residual (Dense R2UNet) Convolutional Neural Network for Segmentation of Lung CT Images. [Paper] [Code] (Course: Computer Vision)

• Deep learning based cardiac MR reconstruction from randomly undersampled sub-Nyquist k-space data. (Course: Biological Imaging Technology)

# Heritage Institute of Technology Undergraduate Research Projects:

Kolkata, India August 2016 - July 2018

• Developed an automatic evaluation and diagnosis algorithm to analyze the optical nerve head for detecting Glaucoma using Machine Learning. [Paper] Later deep-learning architecture was utilized to boost diagnostic capability with 94% accuracy. [Paper] [Code]

### SELECTED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS AND PREPRINTS

- K. Dutta, S. Roy, T.D. Whitehead, J Luo, A.K. Jha, S. Li, J. Quirk, K.I. Shoghi. Deep Learning Segmentation of Triple-Negative Breast Cancer (TNBC) Patient Derived Tumor Xenograft (PDX) and Sensitivity of Radiomic Pipeline to Tumor Probability Boundary. Cancers July 2021. [Link]
- K. Dutta Densely Connected Recurrent Residual (Dense R2UNet) Convolutional Neural Network for Segmentation of Lung CT Images. arXiv Preprint February 2021. [Link]
- R.Mukherjee, S.Kundu, **K.Dutta** and A.Sen. Predictive diagnosis of glaucoma based on analysis of focal notching along the neuro-retinal rim using machine learning. Springer's Pattern Recognition and Image Analysis September 2021. [Link]

#### SELECTED CONFERENCE PAPERS AND POSTERS

- K. Dutta, R.Laforest, K.I. Shoghi. Self-Supervised learning framework to generate preclinical Standard-Count PET from Low-Count PET and multi-objective task-based performance evaluation. IEEE Nuclear Science Symposium, Medical Imaging Conference (NSS/MIC) November 2023, Vancouver Canada [Link] (Oral Presentation)
- K. Dutta, Z.Liu, R.Laforest, A.K. Jha, K.I. Shoghi. Deep learning framework to synthesize high-count preclinical PET images from low-count preclinical PET images. SPIE Medical Imaging 2022:Physics of Medical Imaging February 2022, San Diego USA [Link] (Paper and Oral Presentation)
- K. Dutta, Z.Liu, R.Laforest, A.K. Jha, K.I. Shoghi. Deep learning generation of high count preclinical PET images from low count PET images. World Molecular Imaging Congress, October 2021. (Oral Presentation)
- K.Dutta, R.Mukherjee, S.Kundu, T. Biswas and A.Sen Automatic Evaluation and Predictive Analysis of the Optic Nerve Head for the Detection of Glaucoma. IEEE International Conference on Electronics, Materials Engineering & Nano-Technology May 2018, Kolkata India. [Link] (Paper and Oral Presentation)

### RELEVANT GRADUATE COURSEWORK

Washington University in St.Louis: Large Scale Optimization, Bayesian Methods in Machine Learning, Practicum in Imaging Science, Computer Vision, Theoretical Imaging Science, Machine Learning and Pattern Recognition, Human-in-the-Loop Computation, Mathematics of Imaging Science, Computational Methods of Imaging Science, Biological Imaging Technology, Probability and Stochastic Methods.

# TEACHING AND MENTORING EXPERIENCE

Assistant in Instruction, Washington University in St Louis

January 2022 - May 2022

Guided students on coding assignments and final projects for *Biological Imaging Technology* course. Also delivered supporting lectures, designed assignments and assisted in grading the examination.

### ACHIEVEMENTS AND AWARDS

Best Poster Award - Informatics in Cancer Research (ITCR) 2022, National Cancer Institute (NCI)

Best Student Poster Award - Oncological Imaging Program (OIP) 2022, Siteman Cancer Center

Best Poster Award - WashU Imaging Science Retreat 2022

Outstanding Leadership Award - WashU Imaging Science Mckelvey School of Engineering (2023)

### LEADERSHIP EXPERIENCE

| Graduate Representative, WashU Board of Trustees                  | 2023 - Present |
|---|----------------|
| Graduate Student Ambassador, McKelvey School of Engineering WashU | 2021 - Present |
| Executive Member, Graduate Student Affairs Advisory Board (GSAAB) | 2021 - Present |
| President, Association of Graduate Engineering Students (AGES)    | 2021 - 2022    |
| President, UMANG: WashU Graduate Indian Student Association       | 2020 - 2021    |